<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>An Awakening word to the churches, saints, and professors in this slumbring and sleepy day</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1664</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 41 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 10 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A75826</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing A4277A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R42642</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">38875516</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 38875516</idno>
            <idno type="VID">152183</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A75826)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 152183)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2281:31)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>An Awakening word to the churches, saints, and professors in this slumbring and sleepy day</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>16 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>[s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Printed at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>in the year 1664.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Imperfect: torn and stained, with loss of text.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in: Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Apocalyptic literature --  Quaker authors --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Second Advent.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-06</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-11</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-11</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:152183:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>AN Awakening Word TO THE CHURCHES, SAINTS, AND PROFESSORS; In this Slumbring and Sleepy Day.</p>
            <p>Printed at <hi>London,</hi> in the year 1664</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="tract">
            <pb facs="tcp:152183:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:152183:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>A Brother in Tribulation, and in the Kingdom and Patience of Jeſus Chriſt, To the Elect according to the fore-knowledge of God the Father, called to ſanctification of the Spirit unto obedience, and ſprinkling of the Blood of Jeſus; Together with thoſe yet uncalled, or however diſtinguiſhed, or ſcattered, greeting.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>My Brethren and dearly loved in Jeſus the Chriſt,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>I Say the Truth in Chriſt, I lie not, my Conſcience alſo bearing me witneſs in the holy Ghoſt, that I have great heavineſs and continual ſorrow for you in my heart, out of an earneſt and true Chriſtian-affection to you, and an unceſſant deſire that you may proſper in ſoul and body, and may be made fit, and accounted worthy to ſtand with the Lamb at his appearing upon the Mount <hi>Sion:</hi> But though I have very ſtrong perſwaſions upon my heart, that this Day of the Lord is very very very near, even at the door; yet I have a holy jealouſie upon many, and fear that multitudes, whoſe Names are writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten in the Lambs Book of Life, are wonderfully unfit and unprepared to meet their Lord.</p>
            <p>I am hereupon greatly preſſed in my ſpirit to write in love to ſuch, as a Brother, and beſeech you in the bowels of Jeſus Chriſt to accept it. I have cauſe out of deep ſence and ſad experience in my ſelf, greatly to mourn over the ſin and puniſhment of old <hi>Adam,</hi> as it is manifeſt in me to this very day, which exceedingly darkens the Glory of the <hi>New-Creation</hi> in me; So that by that <hi>Old-man's</hi> abiding ſtill with me, I am greatly hindered from being ſo ſerviceable to Jeſus Chriſt as I would be, and much detained from thoſe Comforts in Divine Injoyments through the Spirit, which I deſire. I cannot indeed terminate the evil of the fleſh in a perſon regenerate, nor am I able to diſcover the wills of the natural heart, or the advantages Satan hath by this <hi>Old man</hi> in the Saints: But this I can ſay of my ſelf, through Grace, <hi>That though I delight in the Law of God, after the inward man, yet I ſee another Law in my Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers warring againſt the Law of my Mind,</hi> (and worſe alſo) <hi>[bringing me into captivity] to the Law of ſin which is in my Members;</hi> So that here, here I am driven out of ſelf, my beſt ſelf, and only by faith in the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe and Covenant, flee to the Mercy-Seat, as ſprinkled with the Blood of the Lamb ſlain from the foundation of the world, and ſo I can ſay with <hi>Paul, — I thank God through Jeſus Chriſt [our Lord;]</hi> I ſay <hi>Our
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:152183:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>Lord;</hi>—and not only my Lord, for he is, Jeſus,—to ſave all his People from their ſins. If this were only my particular ſtate and caſe thus to be burdened with Corruption, hindering me from good, and inclining me to evil, this humble Acknowledgement layes a bond upon you, as Brethren, joyntly to pray for me,—that I might be delivered from this body of death; But alas I may, I may ſay of you all what <hi>Paul</hi> writ to the Churches of <hi>Galatia; — The Fleſh luſteth againſt the Spirit, and the Spirit againſt the Fleſh; and theſe are contrary the one to the other; [ſo that ye cannot do the things that ye would,] but in many [in many things,] we offend all.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I have (the Lord knows) tender bowels to all, yet am I humbly bold to ſay; — That ſuch Perſons (if any ſuch be) as dream of a <hi>Perfection</hi> in the fleſh in this world, are under dreadful deluſions, and give lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle teſtimony of the in-being of the Spirit in them, though they pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend ſo much for it. I judge if ſuch an eſtate in this life in the eſtate of the fleſh were attainable, ſurely God would have magnified that degree of grace to ſome perſons, more or leſs, at one time or other: But I find it only recorded of Jeſus Chriſt, the only begotten of the Father, who had no ſin, and in whoſe mouth was found no guile; for he was God-man, in whom the divine and humane Natures were united in one Perſon, to make him a fit Mediator. Jeſus Chriſt muſt have the true Nature of ſinful man, to pay the price of ſin; and yet he muſt not have the ſin of that Nature, for then he had juſtly ſuffered for his own ſin, and had not been a competent Surety for ſinners, who muſt be himſelf harmleſs and holy. Bear with me though I mention theſe firſt Principles of Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on in this day: for, though according to that Light of the Goſpel, which hath ſhined amongſt us, we might all have been Preachers, yet by our corruptions, together with Satans deluſions, we have ſadly overſlipped the day of the Goſpel-Liberty, and have gained little true ſpiritual Light, God knows, that moſt Saints (I fear) are <hi>babes,</hi> and <hi>but babes in Chriſt</hi> at this day. It will not now recal the day of Goſpel-Liberty a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buſed, to recount Saints failings; but I hope the ſmart of miſ-ſpent time will help the Lord's People better to improve the day of mercy, when mercy again reſtores them. But the Lord knows, well might Saints be overcome with heat of an unwonted (if not unknown) proſperity, while they cannot keep cloſe to God under the Rod. I intend not to ſtay upon this ſubject, but if I miſtake not greatly, I diſcover ſome Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſors (and well it were, if there were but ſome) to be in danger by letting out their hearts too much in lawful things (ſo called at leaſt) I mean in the cares and pleaſures of this life. O Friends, I cannot but mourn deeply to ſee (at this day) ſo many (formerly perſons full of
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:152183:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>life and zeal for Chriſt) now marry themſelves to, and indeed are bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried in the world; ſo that the day of Chriſt is like to come upon them unawares, and I fear they will be found fooliſh virgins at laſt. I do but hint this by the way, but who knows to what ears and hearts the Lord may direct this holy jealouſie by his Spirit, and give ſome poor ſouls that awakening, with ſight and ſorrow for this ſin never more to be ſorrowed for?</p>
            <p>My Brethren; if in the Apoſtles times, thoſe were looked upon and called the laſt times, what then may we judge of theſe times [we are caſt into] who live 1600 years after moſt of the Apoſtles and firſt Saints after Chriſt? Surely, if thoſe were the laſt times, then our times muſt be the laſt part of the laſt times, and the very dregs of evil and ſinful dayes. O! at what a high rate do men ſin now (one or other) who ſlight, or oppoſe the glorious Goſpel of <hi>Free-Grace,</hi> and the remiſſion of ſin in the Blood of the Lamb, Jeſus Chriſt, after this Goſpel hath been ſo eminently preached and witneſſed to, by the Father, the Son, the Spirit, and the Saints, for above 1600 years? The whole time of the <hi>Gentiles</hi> Tyranny was at firſt limitted to 42 Monthes, and the Witneſſes ſackcloth-ſtate to 1260 dayes: and if that time propheti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cally ſhall ſignifie 1260 years, that time muſt now be very near its pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riod, when Chriſt will again aſſume his Supream Power in the World and over the World, according to the Promiſes and Covenant of the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. My Brethren, do but at this day caſt an eye back, and O what a very very little of all the Promiſes, Prophecies, and Viſions too, of the Patriarchs, Prophets and Apoſtles are yet to be fulfilled, if we thorowly conſider it? This very meditation hath been a wonderful help to my faith, when I have looked backward, and found, that from the time (eſpecially) that God called forth <hi>Abraham,</hi> and ingaged himſelf to him by Promiſe and Covenant (in Chriſt,) no one thing failed of all that ever God promiſed to <hi>Abraham</hi> or his Seed, though the moſt of the Promiſes were of great things, and after long time to have accompliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment: very little of all which is yet to be fulfilled at this day. To help you in your meditations, conſider the Prophecies of the ſtate of <hi>Abrahams</hi> Seed in <hi>Egypt,</hi> and how God fulfilled thoſe; Conſider the Prophecies of Chriſt's Incarnation and coming in the fleſh, and how punctually all thoſe have had their fulfillings; Look back to the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phecies of all the monſtrous beaſtly tyrannical Powers of the World, how they have had their actual fulfilling hitherto; Weigh ſeriouſly how Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phecies and Scriptures have had fulfilling in and at Chriſt's death, and how God brought about his own Counſels, and neither men nor Devils could hinder it. Let it be much upon your thoughts thorowly to conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:152183:4" rendition="simple:additions"/>how in all the reign and rage of the laſt Antichriſtian Powers in this Weſtern World, who have far exceeded in Policy, Cruelty and Murder, all the four heathen beaſtly States before them, and in leſs than 1200 years hath ſhed more of the Blood of Saints by Perſecution in this Weſtern Empire, than all the Heathen Pagan Powers have done, take in <hi>Turk, Perſian,</hi> and all the reſt: and that yet God Almighty ſhould in the dayes of theſe Antichriſtian Kings, and in their King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms ſpread the Goſpel, preſerve Saints, and raiſe the Kingdom of his Son, notwithſtanding all their power and rage (according to Promiſe and Prophecy) even where the Whore ſits, and in the Kingdoms of thoſe earthly Kings, over whom the Woman reigns: this is marvellous in my eyes, I ſay, that in all theſe Times and States Jeſus Chriſt ſhould yet preſerve a competent number of Witneſſes, even when and where they were tortured and martyred for their Teſtimony for Jeſus Chriſt, and thoſe beaſtly ſavage Powers yet could neither ſtop their mouthes, nor wear and root them out, as they have attempted, but that they are ſtill increaſed in their number, and in their witneſs for Chriſt againſt the Beaſt; this, this is the manifeſtation of the Power and Faithfulneſs of God to make good his Promiſes, and Covenant, and Oath to <hi>Abraham</hi> and his Seed.</p>
            <p>Now my Brethren, if you ſeriouſly take a view of all theſe Promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes and Prophecies, what, what a little, a very very very little remains to be fulfilled, but the fall of theſe Beaſts, and the exaltation of Jeſus the Chriſt, the Lamb upon the Mount <hi>Sion;</hi> Bleſſed be God, we, we ſee ſo much of the Night is paſt, and therefore the day muſt be at hand: My dearly Beloved, the fields look white to the harveſt, and the crop is ready to cut, yea, the harveſt-man is prepared, he hath his ſharp Sickle in his hand ready to thruſt it in, and the loud Cry of the Angel of the Temple will prevail. I ſay the fields begin to look white to the harveſt; But alas, how few comparatively, even amongſt the Lord's People, are there, who ſhew they either ſee it or believe it? The Lord knows it is a very ſleepy time with the Virgins; their long and ſore afflictions make them heavy, and the night is dark, and there's none to ſay, <hi>How Long?</hi> This ſtay of the Bridegroom (I fear) deadens the Hopes, and ſinks the Faith of many, which ſhould indeed quicken them; Come it will, and that ſuddenly, all believe: And why not now? for certain this great Day of the Lord is very near, our Lord is coming; for his immediate Harbin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers have been ſeen up &amp; down above this three years, Signs in Heaven and Earth, and ſtay long he cannot; therefore why do ye not believe and make ready? Who knows but this very Epiſtle may be the laſt Alarm to awaken ſlumbering ſleeping Saints? therefore ſlight it not. Or who
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:152183:4" rendition="simple:additions"/>can ſay but this may be the laſt Call from Jeſus Chriſt to his Elect in theſe parts, —to come out of <hi>Babylon?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Precious Souls! I have very ſtrong impulſes upon my heart, that I am moved by the Lord in tenderneſs to differing Saints, to write theſe lines, and deal plainly with you, as becomes a Brother: I have no other deſign in it (God knows) but the Glory of Chriſt, the Honour of the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel, and the preſent and eternal Comfort of Saints. I have by Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence been rolled up and down, and caſt into ſeveral Families of Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſors under various Forms, and have been a diligent Obſerver of ſuch perſons as I have been converſant with; ſo that (poſſibly) I may have better ground to write this General Epiſtle, then ſome others of the Lords Servants, who could perform it better then my ſelf. But what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever imperfection any do diſcover in the Pen-man, cover but with Love, and then I know you may diſcern a Voice of the Spirit.</p>
            <p>Brethren, ſuffer, I beſeech you, from me that by exhortation, which is the command of Jeſus the Chriſt,—<hi>Come out of her my People,</hi> (that is, <hi>Babylon</hi>) <hi>that ye be not Partakers of her ſins, and that ye receive not of her plagues: — of her plagues:</hi> This Call is by a Voice from Heaven, or out of the heavenly ſtate; which Call, with the ground moving the Lord Jeſus to give one Call more at laſt to his deceived People, is more fully expreſt by <hi>Jeremiah,—Flee out of the midſt of</hi> Babylon, <hi>and deliver every man [his ſoul,] be not cut off in her iniquity: for this is the time of the Lords vengeance, he ſhall render unto her a recompence:</hi> I beſeech you miſtake me not, I preſs not this ſeaſonable Exhortation upon you as if I inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded to urge a new thing upon you, never heard of before; no, no, I know the Exhortation is old and common, and yet (I fear) the voice of Chriſt is not underſtood in it: I judge the words are frequently uſed and preſs'd in all Forms, yea even in <hi>Babylon,</hi> and by her Prieſts. Now the Light of the Goſpel is ſo gloriouſly broken forth, and groſſer Abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minations are ſo diſcovered, —that the Devil and his Miniſters are fain to transform themſelves into Angels of Light, and learn the Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage of heavenly Saints; and here he plays his laſt Game. Where is that Form of People at this day pretending to worſhip God, but they cry out of <hi>Babylon,</hi> and call—<hi>Come out of</hi> Babylon, yea, even in <hi>Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bylon?</hi> O then what a deep undiſcovered Myſtery is <hi>Babylon!</hi> I profeſs, I know no Form of People pretending Religious Worſhip, but they look upon themſelves as the onely true Worſhippers of God, and their Way the onely true Way of Worſhip, and eſteem all other Wayes falſe and Antichriſtian, and therefore call upon People in other Forms to ſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate, — <hi>Come out of</hi> Babylon, and come to them. Did I not ſpeak this knowingly, from the mouths of Leaders and Teachers, (and I believe
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:152183:5" rendition="simple:additions"/>is known to you all) I ſhould not have dared to to have laid ſuch a charge upon Saints: and what is all this but <hi>Babel</hi> and <hi>Babylon,</hi> Dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and Confuſion? This is the very ſpring and riſe of Perſecution, where the ſtronger Party carries it againſt the weaker or leſſer, like Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thens, or meer men; and is not this <hi>Babylon?</hi> Look well into old <hi>Baby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lon,</hi> or new <hi>Babylon,</hi> and what were the one, or what are the other, but Models and Forms of Civil and Eccleſiaſtical Governments, framed and compiled by ſuch as they took to be the wiſeſt and moſt able men in their times, in great Councils, neither ſeeing nor ſeeking further than humane Reaſon, and the greater Vote; and Laws or Canons thus con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtituted, by the Sword and Power of Fleſh to force and compel Obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence thereunto? And certainly this is <hi>Babylon.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>My Brethren, I confeſs I have a very narrow path to walk in, to deal faithfully between God and his People, and not offend one Party: but I can ſay, (if it were the will of God) I would neither provoke the One, nor offend the Other; yet if I become an Enemy to any, becauſe I tell them the Truth, which they do not know, neither are willing to know, I ſhall beg that the Lord would both diſcover and pardon that ſin alſo, that nothing may keep them from ſeeing the Lord in the Beauties of Holineſs, in the approaching day of Refreſhment.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Object.</hi> But poſſibly a quick Retort is made, That I ſay my Charge too deep, when I charge Saints to be ſtill in <hi>Babylon,</hi> whom they defie: for although the Saints are divided and diſtinguiſhed into many Forms, yet thoſe Forms or Models of Diſcipline and Government they are under, are not formed by the Wit and Wills of men, but from the Word of God, and moſt of theſe Separate-People are ſo far from Perſecution, that they would have none compelled againſt Conſcience; but we ought to ſeparate from evil Perſons and Things.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> Here, here is the great point indeed, which would require a volumn to treat fully on; yet if the Lord would but give in the light of his Spirit in theſe things, <hi>Babylon</hi> was fallen, was fallen indeed, Breaches among Saints were made up, and the Glory of new <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> would ſhine forth preſently; for nothing hinders it (inſtrumentally) but Babyloniſh darkneſs and confuſion amongſt Saints, though yet they ſee it not. This therefore being the main work of our day, to ſeek and beg—That Spirit of Chriſts mouth (the Spirit that gave and reveals the Myſteries of the Goſpel) by which the Lord diſcovers <hi>Babylon,</hi> and will alſo deſtroy her with the brightneſs of his coming, as he is more mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſted to the Saints: I ſhall humbly crave leave to commend ſome pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent brief thoughts to you, and the examination of them to you to im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prove, through the bleſſing of God, by the Spirit in Jeſus.</p>
            <pb n="9" facs="tcp:152183:5" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>Firſt, If I aſſert, <hi>[That moſt Models and Forms for Worſhip, or in which God is worſhipped at this day] are Babyloniſh, and formed by the Wits and Wills of Men, even among Saints;</hi> I can retract my Words, but yet grieve and mourn that it is ſo, and that I ſhould have cauſe in the Name of Jeſus Chriſt to lay ſo deep and dreadful a Charge upon Saints and Profeſſors after ſo long a time of Goſpel light amongſt Us. That the Charge is true, is too manifeſt: For if the various Forms of profeſſing People were directed by the Spirit of Truth, and not by the Wits and Spirits of men, whence then comes all this Babyloniſh Confuſion and Diviſions among Saints both in Doctrine and Order? To charge this evil upon the Spirit of God, is blaſphe my in a high Degree; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the ſin muſt lie upon Saints, for ſo yet I would account them. I ſhall not enlarge upon the ſubject, but muſt take the boldneſs to ſay,— That by want of the Light and Guidance of the Spirit of Truth, poor dark bewildered Saints miſtake their Way and Work: — One taking the Scripture in one ſenſe, another in another ſenſe, and ſo doth a third, a fourth, and a fifth, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and ſo ſuch perſons under ſuch a perſwaſion, (and Light, as they term it, which is Darkneſs oft times) fall into Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties and Forms; and is not this <hi>Babylon?</hi> Yet every Party cries out of <hi>Babylon,</hi> and calls—Come out of <hi>Babylon:</hi> O what hath ſin brought that excellent Creature Man, to! that his Underſtanding ſhould be ſo darkened, and the Man ſo deceived, that he verily thinks that he ſerves God, when indeed he ſerves the Devil! O what hath ſin brought Man to! To take Darkneſs for Light, and Light for Darkneſs! To take Errour for Truth, and Truth for Errour! And yet this is the ſtate of moſt, if not all Saints, in one degree or other. That I may (through Grace) ſpeak home to differing Saints, and clearly diſcover the bottom of Diviſions, and ſet upon the hearts of the Elect a deep conviction of theſe common and dreadful Miſtakes about ſeveral Forms and Models of Divine Worſhip, I ſhall fully demonſtrate to them that while they are in this ſtate, they are in <hi>Babylon,</hi> and that the Lord Jeſus Chriſt hath a ſpecial reſpect to theſe Diviſions, in this laſt call to his People,—<hi>To come out of Babylon.</hi> That I may do this Work with the more clearneſs to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viction, I ſhall obſerve this Order:</p>
            <p>Firſt, Prove that People in this ſtate, are in <hi>Babylon,</hi> or that this ſtate is <hi>Babylon,</hi> where mens own Spirits are their Guides.</p>
            <p>Secondly, Demonſtrate that people in theſe Forms, are not led into them by the Spirit of God.</p>
            <p>This is the Aſſertion I am to prove, —<hi>That thoſe particular Forms and Models of Worſhip and Government, into which People of ſeveral Perſwaſions are formed and united, accounting ſeverally, that onely they in ſuch a Form
<pb facs="tcp:152183:6" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb facs="tcp:152183:6" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="10" facs="tcp:152183:7" rendition="simple:additions"/>have the Spirit of Truth with them, and that all other Perſons and Forms are erroneous, falſe, and to be ſeparated from, as in</hi> Babylon; <hi>and yet this is very</hi> Babylon. I hope it needs not be put upon me to prove that amongſt us there are many Forms of Separate-people under theſe perſwaſions, and in this practice, while both are ſo common; but I judge it not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venient to give them by Name, but proceed to make good my Charge againſt the Thing. Therefore conſider theſe few things ſeriouſly:</p>
            <p>Firſt, That this practice is <hi>Babyloniſh</hi> and from <hi>Babylon,</hi> is evident: for thus myſtical <hi>Babylon</hi> was founded, and raiſed her building—from the Scriptures, as her Leaders and Rulers judged the Scriptures ſpake, or at leaſt as they made them to ſpeak, by corrupting and perverting the Scriptures: Who are ſo ignorant that they do not know that at this ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry day, <hi>Babylon</hi> would father all their Power and Juriſdiction they exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe, even to Idolatry and Murder, upon the Scriptures and <hi>Divine Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority</hi> from God? and yet are <hi>Babylon</hi> for all that, yea, and becauſe of that: Now where do men raiſe their different perſwaſions, but from dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferent taking (or miſtaking) the true and right ſenſe of the Scriptures? all is fathered there, and ſo they make the Scripture ſpeak what their Reaſon or Underſtandings judge to be the minde of the Spirit, and ſo they cloſe: and doth not <hi>Babylon</hi> the ſame, and hath as good Warrant as theſe?</p>
            <p>Secondly, That theſe ſeveral <hi>Sects</hi> and <hi>Diviſions</hi> in and about the Worſhip of God and Government, do ariſe and grow out of the Wits and Wills of Men (as Men) is clear and undeniable upon this ground,— That however perſons in their preſent perſwaſions ſeem high and fixt in their way, pretending the light and leading of the Spirit ſtrongly, and therefore ſeparate from all other forms, and deeply judge and cenſure all differing from them; yet after this, (ſuppoſing they have received better light) theſe very perſons fall into ſome other Form, and ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times into the ſame Form they a little before ſeparated from, as Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſtian and <hi>Babyloniſh;</hi> and the utmoſt they can ſay for their change, is, They were then perſwaded in their Judgements that was the Truth then, and this is the Truth now; and doth not <hi>Babylon</hi> ſay the ſame? Good Lord! what a deep Myſtery is <hi>Babylon</hi> yet to moſt Saints! and what dreadful ſins are the ſins of <hi>Babylon!</hi>— that makes the holy God, the holy Spirit, and the holy Scriptures to be their Authority and War<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant to ſin at this rate! and yet all this while cry,—<hi>Come out of Baby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lon?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thirdly, That theſe <hi>People</hi> and <hi>Sects</hi> are onely formed and founded in the VVits, VVills, and humane Reaſon of Men, alſo is very manifeſt from the Fruits and Effects following them:—VVhat carnal and ſinful
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:152183:7" rendition="simple:additions"/>prejudice, diviſions and cenſuring is there, in theſe <hi>Parties,</hi> of their Brethren, who cannot come up to their preſent thoughts and perſwaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons? However poor ſouls deceive themſelves, and are hurried by blind zeal, yet for certain the fruits moſt appearing in them, are fruits of the Fleſh, and not of the Spirit: for Saints to be divided in heart, and into Parties about Teachers and Forms, ſo as to envy, revile and ſeparate, ſo as to break the Bond of Chriſtian Love and Order, this diſcovers ſuch to be very Babes in the School of Chriſt, and to be more carnal than ſpiritual: This is not mine, but <hi>Paul</hi>'s reaſoning, (1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.3, 4.) and the Argument is not the weaker becauſe it is old,—<hi>Ye are yet carnal: for whereas there is among you envyings, and ſtrife, and diviſions or factions, are ye not carnal and walk as men, or according to man? While one ſaith, I am of</hi> Paul, <hi>and another, I am of</hi> Apollos, <hi>are ye not carnal?</hi> I hope a word to the wiſe is enough, therefore I would onely leave this to conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration, —That <hi>hatred, variance, emulations, wrath, ſtrife, ſeditions, he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſies, and envyings</hi> (Gal. 5.19, 20, 21.) among Saints, in and about the Wayes and Worſhip of God, are really the <hi>fruits of the fleſh,</hi> as well as <hi>Adultery, Idolatry and Murder:</hi> And is it not then high time that the Lord ſhould awaken dreaming deluded Saints, and indeed call them out of <hi>Babylon,</hi> that they loſe not the Light of the Lamb in his Appearing and Glory with his holy Hoſt, and they (outwardly) fall and periſh with <hi>Babylon,</hi> while they think they are in Mount <hi>Sion?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, I ſhall in the next place demonſtrate the foreſaid Poſition negatively, that theſe Forms and Factions are not from the Spirit of God, but ariſe in Peoples own deceived ſpirits, and as hurried by Satan, in ſuch ignorant zeal; the very ſame which ſtirred up <hi>Saul</hi> (after, <hi>Paul</hi>) to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecute the true Chriſtians, and the true Church of Chriſt, (<hi>Act.</hi> 22.3, 4, &amp;c. <hi>Act.</hi> 26.1, 2, 3, &amp;c. <hi>Act.</hi> 21.20, 21.) and thought he did well, and his duty; yea, it is the ſame ſpirit which ſtirred up the Chriſtian Jews to perſecute <hi>Paul,</hi> from miſtaken zeal for the Law: My Brethren, I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeech you hear me patiently, examine and then judge; I aſſure you, my Bowels yern towards you, and Chriſtian Compaſſion moves me onely in the Lord to uſe this plainneſs for the good and comfort of your Souls, and that you may no longer deceive your ſelves; and that when our Lord ſhall come (whom I hope ye look for) he may not find you in <hi>Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bylon,</hi> ſmiting your fellow-ſervants, with heart, tongue, or hand, but that you may be ready to enter into your Lords Joy. Therefore conſider,</p>
            <p>Firſt, Theſe ſinful Sects and Diviſions among Saints, are carnal, fleſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and from mens own ſpirits, and not from the Spirit of God: for the Spirit of God is but one; there is but one God, one Chriſt, one Spirit, and one Way of true ſpiritual Worſhip of God, and not many: This
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:152183:8" rendition="simple:additions"/>the Apoſtle lays down (<hi>Epheſ.</hi> 4.4, 5, 6.) as a general Principle,—<hi>There is one Body</hi> (of Chriſt) <hi>and one Spirit, one Lord</hi> (Jeſus) <hi>one Faith, one Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm</hi> (or Form of true Worſhip) <hi>one God and Father of all, who is above all, and through all, and in you all.</hi> Mark it, there is but one true Myſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal Body of Chriſt, but one Spirit of Truth, but one Faith to Salvati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, but one true Form of Goſpel-Worſhip, but one Lord Jeſus, and but one God and Father of all the Elect by Jeſus Chriſt: Therefore all wayes and forms of Worſhip [but one, revealed by the Spirit of Truth in the Scripture of Truth] are falſe, erroneous, Babyloniſh, and by the wits and wills of carnal deceived men, and not from the Spirit of God.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> Theſe ſad and ſinful Factions and Forms among Saints, are not from the Spirit of Truth, but from their own deceived ſpirits, is thus manifeſted;—The Spirit of Truth teacheth other things, and bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter things than theſe: <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith, <hi>The fruits of the fleſh are manifeſt— Adultery, Idolatry, Murder—Hatred Variance, Emulation, Wrath, Strife; —But the fruit of the Spirit, is Love, Joy, Peace, Long-ſuffering, Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tleneſs, Goodneſs, Faith, Meekneſs, — Gal.</hi> 5.22, 23. I may not enlarge here upon the particular Graces of the Spirit as they put forth them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves in Saints, but I may ſay this in general, —That the Spirit in Saints can diſtinguiſh between Saint and Saint, ſtrong and weak, enligh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tened or dark, Saints at liberty and Saints under temptations; and ſo only the breach is made up, and the wound healed. O Brethren, if we were all acted more by the <hi>Spirit of Grace,</hi> and leſs by our own <hi>carnal ſelfiſh ſpirits,</hi> we ſhould be more like <hi>Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> more full of bowels and compaſſion to the ignorant, and ſuch as are out of the way. I ſhall end this in that healing Exhortation of the Apoſtle, <hi>Gal.</hi> 6.1.—<hi>Brethren, if a man be over-taken in a fault, ye which are ſpiritual, reſtore ſuch a one in the Spirit of Meekneſs, conſidering thy ſelf, leſt thou alſo be tempted.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thirdly,</hi> Theſe ſinful Factions amongſt Saints, are from mens own ſpirits, and not from the Spirit of God and Grace; for they have nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther precept nor practice of Saints in the Goſpel to warrant it, but the contrary altogether. The Old Teſtament is the declaration of one Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant, of one God, one Church, and one Worſhip; The New Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment alſo declares of one <hi>New-Covenant,</hi> one of Jeſus the Chriſt, one Faith, one Baptiſm, one Myſtical Body: yet in that one Body many Members, or that Body divided into many Societies, Companies or Congregations by habitation or near co-habitation; but the whole Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy of Chriſtian Saints living together in one City, or a part in ſeveral Cities or Countries were all of one Faith, in one order of the Goſpel, and all in mutual Love and Fellowſhip as one Body or Church. This was the ſtate of the Primitive Churches of the Goſpel founded by Chriſt
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:152183:8" rendition="simple:additions"/>and his Apoſtles, amongſt which Jeſus Chriſt walked, and amongſt whom the Apoſtles laboured and converſed, and none other: therefore ſuch Societies only are Churches of Chriſt. It is now (the Lord knows) a hard matter to number up the ſeveral Factions of People formed and united in ſeveral Opinions which Chriſt &amp; the Goſpel knows not; and yet every party profeſſing to worſhip God above others, each ſeveral Company accounting their way the only true way of Worſhip, and that only, and ſo they divide and ſeparate from all other Perſons and Forms as falſe, Antichriſtian, and in <hi>Babylon,</hi> while (I fear) their Doctrine and Practices are meerly <hi>Babyloniſh,</hi> and were never known in the Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches of Saints till Antichriſt aroſe. O what a wonderful cheat is An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tichriſt! and what dreadful Darkneſs &amp; Deluſion yet poſſeſſeth Saints, that they take themſelves to be in <hi>Sion,</hi> when indeed they are in <hi>Baby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lon!</hi> and Chriſt knows it is ſo and therefore calls,—<hi>Come out of Her my People.</hi> Poor hearts, I ſpeak my experience (and by light received) my ſoul mourns for you, and mourns after you, and to my Exhortation I joyn my prayers, — That yet the Lord would give forth the Spirit more fully to diſcover your preſent ſtate and ſtanding, for little do you think what ſpirits you are led by. Certainly perſons under ſuch ſingular Opinions diſcover woful pride and ignorance (whoever they be;) and theſe two are the very Baſis upon which <hi>Babylon</hi> is built, and the Pillars upon which ſhe ſtands: remove theſe, and <hi>Babylon</hi> is in the duſt. The better to manifeſt this to you, conſider,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt,</hi> Perſons under theſe ſingular Opinions of their own Light and wayes, ſo as to condemn all others, and ſeparate from them as Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſtian, and account themſelves only to have the Spirit and be the only People of God, and none but they; this diſcovers wonderful pride, arrogancy &amp; raſhneſs; and ordinarily theſe ſingular high thoughts prove but thoughts and miſtakes at laſt. This is a ſad dividing Spirit and Principle of Antichriſt, and diſcovered to creep in early, in <hi>Pauls</hi> time. It was this Spirit which was got into the Church at <hi>Crinth,</hi> which cauſed them to deſpiſe the Apoſtles themſelves, as men of little light, and of ſmall gifts to them: What elſe can we make of thoſe humble Rebukes <hi>Paul</hi> writes to that Church, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.8, 10. — <hi>Now ye are full, now ye are rich, ye have reigned as Kings without us; and I would to God that ye did reign, that we alſo might reign with you: —For we are fools for Chriſt's ſake, but ye are wife in Chriſt; we are weak, but ye are ſtrong; ye are honourable, but we are deſpiſed.</hi> Such a ſpirit alſo was among the <hi>Romans,</hi> which the Apoſtle reproves, <hi>Rom.</hi> 2. <hi>Who make their boaſts of God, and knowing his will, and are able to approve of the moſt ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent things and (are confident) that they are lights to the blind, inſtructors of
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:152183:9" rendition="simple:additions"/>the fooliſh; —who have the form of the knowledge of the Truth: and yet even theſe perſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> cauſed the Name of God to be blaſphemed among the Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiles.</hi> It is, it is a ſhame to mention the pride of deceived Profeſſors, who profeſſing themſelves wiſe (above all others) become fools, or diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cover their weakneſs, being giddy and high-minded, directly oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſite to the Spirit of Saints, the Spirit of Chriſt, his Apoſtles, and the Goſpel, which teacheth more humility, and to look upon the things of others as better than our own. It is wonderful ſtrange that perſons profeſſing the Goſpel, ſhould yet be ſuch ſtrangers to the Spirit of the Goſpel, to ſay no more.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> Theſe ſingular Opinions and Practices, diſcover wonder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>l ignorance and weakneſs, to accuſe their Brethren, and ſeparate from <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hem as in <hi>Babylon,</hi> and this is their own ſtate; nay, poſſibly thoſe they condemn, are nearer to the rule of the Goſpel than themſelves. Sure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly if this charge which ſome Profeſſors lay upon others, ſhall not bear weight in the Ballance of the Sanctuary, the accuſers will be found to ſpeak evil of the things they know not, but by a deceived carnal judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; and that is ſad. When that ſad Diviſion in the Church of <hi>Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rinth</hi> was declared to <hi>Paul,</hi> that they ſaid,—<hi>I am of</hi> Paul, <hi>and I am of</hi> Apollos, <hi>I am of</hi> Cephas, <hi>and I am of Chriſt.</hi> — The Apoſtle chargeth this as a ſin of ignorance, and to convince them, he uſeth this as his main argument;—<hi>Is Chriſt divided?</hi> hath Chriſt ſo many bodies? and leaves them that to conſider. This was ſo contrary to the received Principles of the Goſpel, that he judged the pondering upon that, was enough to diſcover their own carnal thoughts to be the ſpring of ſuch diviſions; for the Spirit of Chriſt and the Goſpel teacheth the quite contrary; —<hi>Love, Joy, Peace, Long-ſuffering, Gentleneſs, &amp;c. bearing one another, burthens, and [ſo fulfilling the Law of Chriſt;]</hi> and therefore <hi>Paul</hi> preſſeth this general exhortation from the Priſon,—<hi>I beſeech you, that ye w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>k worthy of the vocation wherewith ye are called, [with all lowli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and meekneſs,] with long-ſuffering, forbear one another in love, [endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voring] to keep the [unity of the Spirit] in the Bond of Peace,</hi> Epheſ. 4.1, 33. And the ground of this Exhortation the Apoſtle draws from the <hi>Oneneſs</hi> of the Myſtical Body of Chriſt, and of Goſpel-Worſhip, verſ. 4, 5, 6. Alas, alas, the Diviſions among Saints ſufficiently diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver their infant-ſtate, and their new breaking forth of <hi>Babylon,</hi> that they are ſo ſpotted and tinctured with <hi>Babylon;</hi> and no queſtion, but as the Spirit of Light and Truth is more given forth, the Spirit of Antichriſt will be more manifeſt in Satans cloſeſt deluſions, that he cannot de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive long. If I might not too much offend the weak, I could aſcribe a great part of Saints diviſions to ariſe from abuſed Liberty, and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judice
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:152183:9" rendition="simple:additions"/>againſt the able Preachers of the Goſpel; I do not, I dare not acquit them of ſad failings, which have cauſed the way of Truth to be evil ſpoken of, and are an inſtrumental cauſe to move tender and weak Saints to draw into corners, and follow weak and unſound Teachers; (which was their weakneſs alſo) by which means the Miniſters of An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tichriſt and <hi>Babylon</hi> have done their work, and brought the Saints into bondage, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> But amongſt, or above the reſt, I would earneſtly com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend to you three Characters of <hi>Babylon</hi> to be heeded.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt,</hi> Blaſphemy, in denying or invalidating the holy Scriptures.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> In corrupting the pure Doctrine of Juſtification in the Blood of Chriſt, by bringing in the Doctrine of Univerſal Redemption, or Chriſt's dying equally for all alike.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thirdly,</hi> By inſtituting or founding the Church, or Churches, in an Opinion, or ſubmitting to an Opinion, this or that, and not in union with Chriſt. All theſe are in <hi>Babylon,</hi> and from <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>, and will periſh with <hi>Babylon.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Fourthly,</hi> Theſe Factions are <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> not from the Spirit of Grace; and it is too <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="4 letters">
                  <desc>••••</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and forms are great ſtrangers <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> a holy and inward cloſe walking with <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> of Saints cloſet-communion with God; but <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> that is a very lean Religion which ſtayes in the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> is worſe which comes not to the Form of Godlineſs.</p>
            <p>My Paper and Prudence calls me to conclude, and therefore I beg of Saints to look more to their Souls, and to the Duties of Relation natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral, civil and ſpiritual.</p>
            <p>It yet remains that I make ſome reply to the latter part of the Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jection; —<hi>That theſe perſons are againſt force and perſecution for Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, but where perſons walk diſorderly, to withdraw and ſeparate.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For my part, I cannot ſay that all Corrections or reſtraint in abuſes and corruptions in and about the Worſhip of God under the Goſpel, is Perſecution; yet I do confeſs, that withdrawing or ſeparating from falſe Wayes and falſe Worſhip, is a bleſſed Ordinance of God when rightly uſed; but for Saints to ſeparate from Saints, and withdraw from Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, and ſo un-ſaint the one, and un-church the other upon mens own bare opinions or ſelf-conjectures, and not in the Ligh, Spirit and Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of Chriſt, becomes a ſin of a high nature. Alas, many people know not what ſpirit they are led by, and it is much to be feared a change of ſtate may change their minds in ſome things as well as in others.</p>
            <p>My <hi>Brethren,</hi> in tender Chriſtian <hi>Bowels</hi> I have written theſe lines to you, and ſhall follow them with earneſt and conſtant prayer, that the
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:152183:10" rendition="simple:additions"/>Lord would direct them ſeaſonably to gracious ſouls by the Spirit of Grace and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="4 letters">
                  <desc>••••</desc>
               </gap>th, that they may be made effectual to thoſe great ends I have deſigned them to, <hi>Love, Unity</hi> and <hi>Peace</hi> amongſt all Saints, and ſo ſhut up this Epiſtle in the words of <hi>Paul,</hi> 1 Cor. 1.10. — <hi>Now I beſeech you, Brethren, by the Name of the Lord Jeſus Chriſt, that ye all ſpeak the ſame things, and that there be no Diviſions or Schiſms among you; but that ye <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> perfectly joyned together in the ſame mind, and in the ſame judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in all the things of God, Chriſt, Spirit, Goſpel and Saints, and things accompanying your peace and joy here, and glory hereafter.</hi> Amen. Even ſo come Lord Jeſus, and thus rule and reign.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>
                  <hi>From my Clift in the Rock,</hi> 
                  <date>
                     <hi>the 10th day of the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>th month,</hi> 1664. I hope in the year of Redemption</date> (begun) from <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</dateline>
            </closer>
            <trailer>THE END.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
